[Music]
Jordan Peterson Peterson mr. Peterson
Canadian psychology professor is
somebody people love or love to hate so
Patricia I know that your interest in
Jordan Peterson was well before the sort
of controversy that happened sort of
starting in 2016
can you tell me why you were interested
in in him and how long ago have you been
interested in doing a film with him I
first came across Jordan's work in 2003
back when I was a psychology undergrad
student I was taking a lot of philosophy
classes I was very much in the world of
the big existential questions trying to
find my way you know lost early 20s
something and I came from a pretty
religious Roman Catholic Italian family
I moved away from religion and there was
something about Jordans book that I felt
kind of went down to that religious
level and a lot of the talks that I
later saw coming out on TV oh and in
Canada were about things like the
necessity of virtue it was engaging with
these ethical and kind of religious
questions so it sort of filled in that
gap for me and I was also interested in
the way that he talked about the idea of
the divine individual and that there's
um you know there's there's a divinity
to to paying attention to what you're
interested in and and where that takes
you and it's not just something
frivolous there's there's a real
importance to and kind of like a purpose
that comes with you paying attention to
and following like that was a really
important guide for me and actually
something that guided me towards later
pursuing this film I felt
like it was something really important
for me to do but I didn't understand why
and it was especially his introduction
to maps of meaning where he talked about
having had nightmares during his teenage
years about the end of the world and he
was trying to decipher the nature of
evil and not only this broad question
but it was something personal to him so
I was interested in the ideas but I was
also interested in the person behind the
ideas and so I finally reached out to
him in 2015 about making a film
interestingly one of the ideas that led
me to his book maps of meaning early on
was just from reading different
philosophers I sort of came to this
conclusion that you can have two people
in the same room you know in the same
place at the same coffee table in front
of them but your belief system and the
way you frame the world informs reality
to the extent where we can literally be
in two different realities even if we're
beside each other and this was like a
big aha moment for me of well we're kind
of screwed like how can people really
understand each other and resolve
conflicts and I remember that being the
initial thing that somehow led me I
think through so at Google search to
maps of meaning so it's interesting how
I you know later found myself working on
this film about Jordan's comments on
Bill c16 involving into all of this
other these other issues of political
correctness but with with this idea of
culture war looming underneath all of
that so it's been I guess an evolution
of a lot of different ideas and given
that you're kind of interest was much
more in kind of mythological and his
ideas what did he think or what did he
feel at the time when all of the the the
c16 stuff started taking over was a
feeling of all fantastic I'm following a
really a live story or was it kind of
like oh this is not the direction I
wanted this film to go in was it both
for those it's interesting because I
guess the film kind of morphed a couple
of times because initially was about the
ideas but then it started
the film became about following Jordan
and his friendship with Charles Joseph
and Jordans renovations to his home how
he was adding a third story Charles's
family was adopting Jordan and giving
him a name in qua quality Aras
indigenous language so I had already
decided to shift from ideas to how the
ideas manifest in his life and I thought
well that's a more interesting Avenue to
pursue for a film so I was already kind
of taking a human approach but then the
thing I didn't expect was I would I
didn't start off with an intention of
making a film about political issues as
well so I would say that came as a
surprise I don't think I ever felt like
oh well this isn't where I want the film
to go but it was uncomfortable for me
for sure but the way I see the
filmmaking process is you know it's it's
in a way I mean it's an honor and a
privilege to to be able and hard work to
be making a film about something and I
think when you're really engaging in the
artistic process it's like you're
becoming a vessel to to showcase this
thing so it's like it's not up to you
you have no idea where it's gonna take
you you have to just kind of follow
where it leads and it's hard it can be
really uncomfortable it certainly was
for me but I learned a lot along the way
and I I always felt dedicated to
pursuing it regardless of where it took
me what the reception been like and has
it surprised you in any way it's been so
interesting to release the film because
we had television cut a 44 minute
version of this film released a year ago
in Canada only and I think it's been a
bit of a surprise for us to now release
a longer version of the film and to run
in more controversy even though it's
it's pretty similar to the first film
that we released to the one extent we
weren't surprised because we know how
dividing Jordan's name can be in a room
and
how he still is controversial among the
the arthouse and kind of left wing which
has become mainstream culture but we
were hoping to get more of a release in
the art house and mainstream theaters
but then I guess the most surprising
part was the theater the theater
cancellations that we got so we had a
week-long run canceled in Toronto we had
another screening canceled in Brooklyn
and another one canceled in Toronto
another one that we were trying to set
up in Houston that didn't happen because
they were afraid of controversy so the
interesting thing about the
cancellations is they were all because
of staff complaints so it wasn't the
curators themselves like they had
already said yes but then the staff
complained feeling like well most cases
they hadn't seen the film but they felt
like it would be unsafe to have Peterson
fans coming to the theater but it's
always been very important for us to
have a theatrical release of the film
because we want to be in the room with
people when they see the film it's such
a conversation starter we had a lot of
test screenings in our living room where
we had such interesting conversations
with a diverse group of people watching
the film so we wanted to replicate that
through a theatrical release the people
that came to see the film I mean you
know people really respected the film
they enjoyed watching all the intimate
stuff you know there's a lot of you know
primary content there and like if you're
if you're a fan of Jordan you see the
film and you feel almost like an
intimacy to the guy because you're there
in his room you're there having
breakfast with Tammy you know so people
really get a kick out of that but then
when it came to the ideas and the kind
of the politics they were surprised I
think about how balanced the film is and
that we never used it for example to
trans activist as a punch line you know
it would've been very easy to do that it
would have probably been more lucrative
to do that because partisanship pays
that's what I've learned going on this
tour but at but at the same time these
these Peterson fans that came out and
chatted us up afterwards
they really respected that they like the
that certain things were challenging in
the film and how we showed the two
different sides as best we could but
focusing on the human part like who are
these people why did they think the way
they think and it was a great example of
a documentary documents reality
realities messy and hard to figure out
you can't do it overnight so we like
that people got that even though they
didn't expect that and maybe almost
maybe even expected something like a
robber
sjw's are ruining everything you know we
definitely show the overreach of the
left of course because we talk about the
free speech issues that happen that you
have tea here but we quickly go into
kind of who is this guy and what is his
life like what is what is what has this
been like for Jordan so that people
really appreciated so that felt good it
felt really nice to get that after these
cancellations you know and in the film
there's this one scene where Jordan puts
a mask on his face and it sort of says I
think it's something about which one is
the real Jordan so this is what I
actually look like a nemesis where
people who don't like you think I live
like
[Music]
yeah that's a good question while I
would say they're both real I think
maybe Patricia you ask him which one is
true and he says well that they're both
true what do you think he meant by that
yeah so that was such an impromptu
moment of just setting up for an
interview with him and I always loved
that moment because I think it speaks
volumes and there's all these layers to
it right so on the one hand Jordan talks
about the idea of the monster and how
it's important to encounter your dark
side and he's very young and influenced
of course and so on the one hand I think
he's saying you know I'm human I'm this
normal person but I'm also a monster and
in order to be a good person you also
need to be a monster you need to have a
knife but not necessarily use it but but
know that you're not going to take
advantage of me kind of thing so I think
that's what he means there and how was
your opinion of him been changed by
making the film so I came across him as
someone speaking about profound ideas
that were really interesting and
impactful for me I was in my early 20s
and he was addressing the big
existential questions and the kind of I
came from a very religious family but
went away from religion and so there was
something about his work that was going
down to that level that would kind of
fill in the gap of at least engaging in
that religious space I would say so by
the time I reached out to him to make a
film about him in 2015 after having had
this idea at the back of my mind for
many years for me he was this kind of
larger-than-life figure which is very
interesting because now he's this
larger-than-life figure for most people
and for me he's a human being but I kind
of had this like reverse experience of
that so it's been a kind of
roller-coaster ride I would say when he
released those the videos the professor
gains political correctness videos it
came as a surprise to us we didn't know
the videos were coming we didn't know
how much he was thinking about this
stuff you know we had some
preliminary conversations with him about
political correctness but the Jordan
Peterson that I knew before that his
views about that stuff was at least you
know the way I knew of him as a
professor in public speaker those things
were more hidden so this was definitely
a very new step for him to be coming out
and speaking so publicly and kind of
advocating for specific things so that
was new I would say it was well it was
very uncomfortable for me that the you
know the hill he chose to a stick as a
pole and was about trans pronouns and
human rights law I understand why that
raised a lot of red flags for people I
mean you're criticizing a human rights
law it's like whoa what what what's
going on with that guy I understand that
reaction so it was an uncomfortable
process but it also forced me to dig
deeper into a lot of issues that I
wasn't that I didn't realize and that I
wasn't thinking about on a deep enough
level or that I didn't know how to
articulate what was really going on
about so it forced a lot of that kind of
thinking for me and I guess I would say
fundamentally it just witnessing Jordan
go through this tumultuous period of his
life just revealed how human he is to me
so I guess it's going from for me him
being this larger-than-life figure to
really this this human being that's
trying to adapt as this this crazy
phenomenon is emerging in his life he's
trying to stand up for something he
believes in and there's things that I
agree with things that I disagree with
but but fundamentally just like seeing
then how he would adapt to all of that
and also the toll that it's taken on him
and his family and friends so I think
it's it's shown me the the human
vulnerability and it's been this weird
kind of like splintering off of seeing
him as a person but then witnessing him
through media interviews and all these
different stories people are telling
about him as kind of a confusing
experience as well
and then to kind of talk about back to
your question about have I seen a change
in Jordan man I mean with all of these
interviews of people trying to corner
him or to kind of criticize them
unfairly on a mainstream platform I can
totally see how it could make somebody
get really rigid in doing okay well I'm
not gonna I'm not going to give an inch
I'm not gonna make a concession the war
radicalizes you it hardens up your skin
it says well fuck it I'm gonna keep my
cards close to my chest I'm not gonna
give you a concession because you're
just gonna fuck me over later that's
kind of what happened and it was a shame
because polarization breeds polarization
and it's it's hard to blame the guy for
that because he's gone through so many
of these interviews and I've had just
the little instances with these mom
unfortunately now maybe but you do see
that hardening I do see yeah I do see
that kind of like this over emphasis on
this kind of like a right-wing guy who
doesn't give a shit about you he just
wants to use this situation to make
liberals look stupid so they could win
an election
this kind of buddy-buddy thing without
really being skeptical of this guy and
then on the other hand if a left winger
sneezes it's a it's a you know it's a
blog post you know so I kind of felt a
little bit of that seeing all the
content that's out there and if you look
at the the opening of the film it starts
off with this scene of Jordan in 2015
with his family and they're doing his
personality test on himself it was in
its beta mode at that point and Jordan
is visibly different it's before he
changed his diet I think his diet at
that point was you know fries and Diet
Coke I think in between classes there
was like the fries truck outside that's
what I could see him eat but in this
scene you just see a lightness to him
and the way his family teases him and
they joke that's a lightness that we
haven't seen in Jordan in a long time
I've heard
Jordan Peterson described as a kind of
one-man lightning rod for the culture
war which seems pretty accurate over the
last couple of years what was it like
for you guys being in the middle of that
because I think your
as you've said before you're from a much
more sort of artistic probably
left-leaning background what was that
like being being in that kind of
Maelstrom what did he learn from it so
much it was hard at first the first year
especially things were so tense in
Toronto it was very difficult for me to
get certain people to agree to be part
of the film just immediately saying you
know it's a film about Jordan Peterson
well people's garters are up and they're
wondering well what are my intentions
and rightfully so I understand but
especially when you know the opposition
side is saying well don't give him a
platform it's like a film about it even
if my intentions are to make sense of it
and try to understand it which they were
and I wasn't necessarily sympathetic to
everything he was saying it didn't
really matter if the idea is well don't
give a platform to the discussion itself
so that made it really challenging and
being in certain documentary circles it
was nerve-wracking to say well I'm
working on the Jordan Peterson film but
then that started to shift as he became
more and more popular and gain more
ground and then suddenly all these
filmmakers are flocking to him and
everybody wants a piece and and then it
kind of shifted to you know having to
feel kind of like protective about what
we were working on and had invested so
much into and you know even learning
about strange phone calls that took
place of people trying to sabotage deals
we were trying to get to fund the film
which is it's so strange because it was
also this is my first feature film so
yeah it was all it was all I guess very
tumultuous and things were happening
very quickly every week there was a new
drama
taking place to try to delve into and
for a while I mean what I thought the
film was about in the first year changed
from what I thought it was about in the
second year and even the third year at
all it evolved and I guess I let the
story kind of guide me as it was
evolving to then figure out okay what
what are we actually going to focus in
here and when we when it came to editing
later I realized I probably shot kind of
three different films because well I
learned how hyper focused you have to
really be for a film to be cohesive but
yes it was confusing but I'm so grateful
for the many things that we learned
about yeah politically and culturally I
mean that my bubble burst when Trump was
elected I didn't see that coming I
didn't take him seriously so I've
learned so much about what was taking
place underneath the surface leading to
that and it makes so much sense now and
and I think it's um it's it's helped my
own views to become less superficial in
a way where I would never question you
know things like can empathy go too far
I would never question things like that
before all of this took place for me
when I would shock to me I didn't know
that much about I just through this
experience man for a good number of them
I just lost so much respect for
progressives they're so called because
I'm some of them yeah some of them you
know and because it's like it's kind of
like this reverse racism thing where
it's like the taller the whiter the
straighter the person is if if they COFF
it's it's a sign of bigotry you know
it's it's like this weird thing where
it's like kind of like the last page in
Animal Farm where it's like now the
progressives won when in the heyday they
were the counter of you know the
revolutionaries the counterculture we
have to strive for civil rights but they
did and they won it just surprised me
how much they would turn on their own
seemingly their own principles and also
none of them would speak up against a
more loudmouth version of what they of
their tribe when when one person says
something kind of crazy nobody says
anything because they're scared and they
don't want a fish if they're white they
don't want to come off as racist and but
they're gonna lean in at the bar later
on that night lean in with their friends
and talk about what they want to talk
about and then some of those people are
going to end up being Trump supporters
again like Trump will probably win again
and it's like okay that's not good
because a conservative are just not a
progressive should have more options
than a guy like that but unfortunately
they don't right now and you mentioned
Patricia the the filming with Charles
Joseph the quack-quack right Quaqua yeah
I'll let you say that so that that was
one of the the main features that you
were initially following can you talk
about that what material what attracted
to that story and what material do you
have that you'd be hoping to put into a
new film so I approached Jordan first in
spring 2015 at the time with an interest
in making a film about his ideas and his
work I think the initial film title was
something like between chaos and order
and then as I started to learn more
about what was happening in his life he
told me that he was adding a third story
to his home that was being modeled after
an indigenous longhouse and I thought
okay that's interesting and I learned
about his friendship with Charles Joseph
who's carver who lived in the northern
part of Vancouver Island and they've
known each other for about 15 years just
sort of met at an arts fair yeah but 15
years ago and it's developed into this
really interesting friendship where
there's such different people Charles is
this raw artist he he's also a
residential school survivors so Canada
has this dark history of having taken
Native kids away from their families at
a young age and put them into
residential schools and many many of
them were sexually abused including
Charles so this happened to him at the
age of six and he was in the school for
eight years so he had this whole life of
trauma that he was trying to move past
and he's still working on that of course
and he he never learned how to read
because of his experience in school and
it's something that in recent years he'd
learned how to do and he's now texting
us and that sort of thing meanwhile you
have this formerly Harvard professor
who's extremely articulate who really in
Myers the artistic capacity of Charles
and how he just lives as this true
artist and so they complement each other
in these interesting ways they're so
different but they also place an
interesting emphasis on the dream world
and the way that the this film which I
intend on going back to make now it was
for a year and a half I was working on
it until Jordan made the videos and then
the rest is history
but it's tentatively called Mahalo which
is a Kwok will award that's Charles's
language and that means to dream so I
really want to explore the dream world
Charles has very vivid dreams tan me as
Jordan likes to say Tammy dreams for the
both of them because Tammy's the one
that has the vivid dreams and then
Jordan links to analyze and interpret
them and I have this one scene where
Jordan Tammy and Michaela are talking
about a dream a dream Tammy had of there
was this kind of shamanic character that
was getting away and the person in the
dream who Tammy thought was her self but
Jordan thought with him so that person
was trying to to catch that that
character and it was it was very
important I think they were getting away
on a horse or something like that and I
later asked Jordan why do you think you
had to catch him and he said because
otherwise we would we would be losing
our tradition something something to
that effect and so it was so interesting
working on a film that was on that level
to them how all this political stuff
happened because it resulted in things
like the month of October in 2016 this
is this was you know one of the most
heated points in the controversy where
the articles were just starting to come
out and journalists were questioning
Jordan in trying to figure out what is
this guy really about and at the same
time Charles and his chief and some
family flew over to Toronto to bless
this space in Jordan's home and that's
when naming ceremony took place where
Jordan was given his sacred name and
Quoc Willa and it was so strange to to
see those things happening at the same
time
he's been given a name and then he's
been calling been called other names in
the media at the same time and other
footage that I have is a really special
potlatch ceremony and that's where
Charles's family was officially adopting
Jordan and his family into his that took
place in spring 2016 I think it was so
there's this big bonfire and the big
house and Jordan is kind of dancing
around it being blanketed it was such a
different film that we were working on
before all of this changed so I intend
on going back and finishing that film
once this tour is over at this film I
would say one similarity between the
films though is that they're both kind
of human and honest like there's this
one choice scene it's it's so good like
Patricia's in the back of the car and
Jordan and Charles are driving to Truth
and Reconciliation Commission meeting
which is a an event for talking about
what happened in residential schools and
Jordan asked Charles what's been the
hardest thing and Charles says smell the
smell of white people so he would be he
would be taken to a room called Bible
study you know but there wasn't the
Bible in it it's just this dark room and
he's being molested in there so he
closes his eyes as a little kid and all
the other senses are heightened and you
would never ever forget the smell of the
priests and it's it's really poignant
because Jordan is Charles's first white
friend right and they're having this
super candid moment just very honest
very raw talking about past trauma and
that's that I'm really excited about
that film because it's so human it's
interesting that you bring up this idea
of human because that's also been an
interesting shift of going from working
on mahalo to the rise of jordan peterson
because it's like there was this point
in time where suddenly it was no longer
ethical to make a human film and and
that was really strange because you felt
that's all I felt
I didn't know I didn't feel that but I
felt like the kind of outside pressures
of I guess what's become kind of more
normative documentary culture or kind of
left-of-centre mainstream culture it's
like like when when I was getting
feedback from certain people in early
stages of the film who were very much in
opposition to Jordan they didn't like
feeling any sense of appeal to Jordan's
charisma at points in the film or or I
think - even just taking a liking to his
human side at any points it was like
there's a danger to humanizing him
because then it it softens the the point
of view of know what he did is wrong and
there's there's a hard line here did you
think that that was right I would say it
was it was confusing and uncomfortable
but I didn't think it was right I still
made a human film and in fact I thought
it was even more important to make a
human film because we were so aware of
the culture war being the undercurrent
throughout all of this and the thing
that so easily lost is the humanity of
all of these people it's like we need to
see Jordan as a human but we need to see
his opposition as humans as well and so
that was fundamentally very important
for us to portray all of these people
with dignity in the film because you'll
typically just see a YouTube channel
with a video coming from let's say it's
coming from the right and it's you know
Jordan is the intelligent hero and the
sjw's are irrational and SJW tears or
whatever it isn't like and that's all
you see and what we witnessed was just
so much more complex than that
and you mentioned before that you found
it difficult to persuade some people to
be in the film that's been a an issue I
think for a lot of people making films
about these kind of these kind of
subjects for example I know with
evergreen Brett Weinstein's experience
with evergreen it was much harder to
find people on the other side like Brett
was obviously keen to sell his story and
but it's often I I know from my
experiences off
harder to find people who are willing to
take the other side of that because they
see that kind of collaboration with with
a film about say Jordan Peterson would
be tantamount to platforming him and all
the rest of it so how was that
experience for you trying to get people
to go on the record yeah it was
definitely difficult but I kind of
persevered through and I think what
helped in the end was trying to be
genuine when asked questions about well
what's my own background what's my own
interest and what am I trying to get at
with the story and I think what also
helped was that because I didn't chase
that story but it was more like the
controversy came to me because of the
position I was already in I didn't have
a strong position on either side well
you know he's right about this or you
know I I wasn't coming at it from a
political perspective I was coming at it
from a human perspective so it made my
curiosity genuine it made my pursuit to
make sense of what was going on genuine
and although I came into it with a big
interest in Jordans ideas I also had a
background of being more politically
left-of-center so put me in this kind of
perfect like conflicting situation where
I could empathize with people from all
sorts of perspectives coming at this and
and I thought it was important to really
ground myself in that even though it
made it a conflicting and confusing
process I thought that was important to
give the film integrity and for people
to see this genuine curiosity in in me
wanting to listen to them as opposed to
just peg them into you know a specific
side to serve my own agenda and the film
and has it affected changed your sort of
political views or cultural views how
would you wear it wherever you ended up
at the end of this process yeah I love
that I love that question okay so for me
did you get read pilled yeah for a
moment I guess for then I kind of grew
that for me yeah it was just like look
challenge some of these left-wing things
that we just take by default so if
you're living in the city you come from
an immigrant family you turn on TV or
YouTube or whatever it is and you listen
to the top people things are generally
left-leaning okay I guess because they
won the culture war you know I don't
know and sometimes when you're not when
you're doing other things or you're not
politically minded on your own you can
take certain points of view as default
inclusivity diversity inclusion course
that all sounds lovely and great let's
I'll sign that and where your button you
know come to your hold up your banner or
whatever it is at school so this whole
thing with Jordan and talking with him
and with the people that I met through
him it challenged some of my left evap
beliefs the shaky ones the superficial
ones they weren't even really my beliefs
they were just kind of like rented from
people that I liked that are charismatic
that are on TV that are make Hollywood
films or whatever it is and it just kind
of gets compounded over the years and so
you take them and you kind of forget
that they're not your own because you
keep saying it and saying it and so but
but this whole challenge of this kind of
being at the border of like the left and
the right I guess from kind of traveling
between two tribes has shaken out the
more superficial ones are the ones that
were never really my ideas you know so
that's been good I feel more confused
though but something closer to I want
the things that I say to be the things
that I do and less about making other
people happy online or virtual signaling
or putting something out there to get a
response so that's been a really good
evolution for me and I'm really happy it
happened at the time it did Patricia
where have you ended up I'm not even
sure maybe I would have to do one of
those political questionnaires
I don't I don't think that I have
fundamentally shifted too much where I
am on the spectrum because I don't think
my values have changed or my personality
of course hasn't changed but I think
I've just become more open-minded to
understanding where where conservatism
comes from really and being more
open-minded to to listening to that and
seeing value in it and I mean I probably
have moved more to the center maybe then
I was before because I I think had
become more superficially moved towards
the left and an unquestioning and butBut
I think it's kind of brought me back to
a place of where I used to be but it was
just kind of maybe going along with
where culture was going without really
paying attention to it like one of the
things that going through this the
process of making this film has made me
think about was back when I was in
university I was part of a student Club
that made this magazine called
perspectives and the goal of it was to
put out a controversial question and ask
students faculty and staff what do you
think about this and why so it wasn't a
poll it wasn't like you know yes or no
what's your vote it's like what do you
think and think deeply about why and
write it all out so you can think about
and so others can learn about why you
think what what you do and then we also
looked at whatever the question was we
looked at it from different perspectives
so different kind of framing so our
first issue was about what do you think
about same-sex marriage and why cuz at
the time this was a big topic in Canada
and and it's so strange to even think
about that now cuz I feel like I'm like
aging myself like that feels like
something that'd be centuries ago and in
a way it's it's embarrassing to even ask
like what what do you think about
same-sex marriage it's just so
interesting how culture shifts over time
and when I think about it now I don't
know how a magazine like that would do
on a campus I mean I know there are
clubs forming a lot of them are actually
influenced by Jordan Peterson as we've
seen on this tour that are about the
critically and we met this great one in
New York that was inspired by the idea
of steel Manning which was used during
the Jordan Pederson Sam Harris debates
right like let's start this off by steel
Manning your opponent what a beautiful
concept it really enables you to
understand think through empathize with
where that other side is coming from and
and helps you to think more clearly so
in many ways I think working on this
film has brought me back to that place
that I used to be in and and kind of
like reintegrate parts of myself that
were lost and you mentioned sort of the
impression that you've had touring the
film as well how would you summarize the
impact that you think Jordan Peterson
has had over the last two years from
what you've seen making the film and
then going and visiting all the places
that were influenced by his thought so I
guess there's there's the political
impact and then there's the personal
impact there are some people that aren't
even really interested in the political
stuff at all aren't interested in
hearing about Bill c16 political
correctness they just love his book
twelve rules for life and they're really
coming at it from the perspective that I
guess I was initially coming at it when
I knew of his work in maps of meaning so
we found a lot of those people I would
say who are just kind of really
interested in those ideas and he's
Jordan has those people are just so
enthusiastic and kind of willing to do
anything to help just because it's it's
like pulled them out of this stuck state
that they were in in their lives and
those reactions don't surprise me even
seeing the level to which those
reactions have skyrocketed throughout
this period because I saw those things
happening before he became famous at
public intellectual but they were
happening happening at a much smaller
scale but in his class it was when I
would go to them in 2014 or 2015
students would all line up after class
and crowd around him and just want their
five minutes to ask him a question so
there was always this depth to the kinds
of things
was talking about that would go to that
level that would help people kind of
just have moments of insights and put
ideas together and and come out of
apathy and confusion if it's almost like
he's he's doing for people with words
and philosophy what music and art can do
so so there's that side of things but
then there's of course the people that
are really inspired by him speaking out
politically I had one comment I think
from a student in Texas who said well we
always there are a lot of films about
the the the liberal heroes and or the
you know the people on the liberal side
and so thanks for making one about a
conservative oh well that's that's an
interesting comment from for me I think
of a Fight Club
so when flight club came out I was in
grade 9 and I remember this one line
from that where a generation of men
raised by our mothers so when we and I
kind of knew this before but when I meet
them when I met them on tour I was like
yes like there's a lot of guys here that
either didn't have dads or maybe their
dad was a bit too kind of masculine and
too hard on them and they didn't know
how to talk to their own dad or maybe a
little bit too feminine a little bit too
soft a little bit kind of ladies are
fair about things then you got Jordan on
YouTube right where the these boys are
already at and talking about things in a
you know offering structure offering
kind of helps hints and everything that
that helped them to kind of guide their
life so that was really that was really
nice to finally meet them and but yeah
like they less or some of these guys you
know they kind of see Jordan as their
dad you know like it's like and they get
very sensitive online but yeah when I
met them I was like it's yeah they they
really look up to this guy and they
Jordan has really helped them like they
because Jordan writes in a way that's
accessible you know and that isn't too
too heady like maps of meaning is a hard
read but 12 rules for life is accessible
to a lot of guys
so I think that's good as I it was
really cool to finally meet the people
that have been influenced so positively
by Jordans life and by Jordan's work
that makes me think of another comment
we got I think it was also in Texas so
in the poster of the film we kind of
show all the different pieces all the
media all the the people the social
media all contributing to the the kind
of co-creation of Jordan as the persona
of Jordan Jordan as this mythological
figure and in the film we also kind of
have these like chapters headed by
different stories being told about
Jordan for the same reason because of
this kind of splintering that we
experienced throughout the making of
this film and kind of like the the you
know there's Jordan the human and then
there's all of this so one of the
figures that we have in the film sorry
on the film poster there's the the kind
of left side and the right side one of
the figures on the right side is a
person who's holding a mask of Jordan
and so it's kind of like the person who
really admires Jordan and then tries to
tries to be like him tries to speak like
him starts to use his words and but it
gets to a point where he's like you know
he's not really in touch with himself
and what he even thinks but he's
imitating Jordan and there was a someone
that came up to me after and he said I
love seeing that on the poster because
that used to be me and he he eventually
started to become self aware of it and
grew out of it but it was kind of a
phase he had to go through and in the
growth process of this so it's it was
really cool having someone you know
comment and relate to that but then also
have that that awareness and and growth
and and be able to have the
vulnerability to admit and say well yeah
I used to be him and it's not like you
know we're above what's on the poster I
think it's like there's a little bit of
everybody in there and everybody has you
know love or hate Jordan has kind of
contributed to him exploding into this
larger-than-life figure
rebel wisdom is a new sense making
platform bringing together the most
rebellious and inspiring thinkers from
around the world if you're enjoying our
content then you can help us make more
by becoming a subscriber which will give
you access to a load of exclusive films
also you can then join our group zoom
cause to discuss the ideas and the films
and you can send us ideas for questions
for upcoming interviews we're also
looking for talented people to help us
out with editing graphics music that
kind of thing and if you're a regular
viewer you'll know we talk a lot about
the value of embodying or actually
living out the ideas that we talk about
so that's why we run regular events in
London check out the links on the
website for more and hope to see you
soon